<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True and happy newes from Worcester read in the honourable House of Commons, Septem. 24, 1642 sent in a letter from His Excellencie the Earle of Essex upon Saturday the 24 of September, 1642 to the House of Commons : wherein is declared a famous victory by Master Fines a member</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277841</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">197689</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197689)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 247:E118, no 43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True and happy newes from Worcester read in the honourable House of Commons, Septem. 24, 1642 sent in a letter from His Excellencie the Earle of Essex upon Saturday the 24 of September, 1642 to the House of Commons : wherein is declared a famous victory by Master Fines a member</title>
                  <author>Essex, Robert Devereux, Earl of, 1591-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Septem. 26. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646.</term>
               <term>Rupert, --  Prince, Count Palatine, 1619-1682.</term>
               <term>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197689:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>True and happy Newes From <hi>WORCESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read in the Honourable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Septem.</hi> 24. 1642.</p>
            <p>Sent in a Letter from His Excellencie the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> upon Saturday the 24 of <hi>September,</hi> 1642. to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Wherein is declared a Famous Victory by Maſter <hi>Fines</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons over Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> who came to the ſaid City with 500. Horſe, upon Thurſday laſt.</p>
            <p>Relating alſo the ſame Deſcription of the Battell and the number that was ſlaine on both ſides,</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the proceedings of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſince his comming to the ſaid City expreſſed in the ſaid Letters.</p>
            <p>Together with His Reſolution concerning the City of <hi>London,</hi> being happy tydings for all thoſe that wiſh well to this happy Reſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed for <hi>Tho. White. Septem.</hi> 26.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <pb facs="tcp:197689:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:197689:2"/>
            <head>True and Happy Newes from <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Thurſday laſt Prince <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> marched towards <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> with his Army, being in number 500. Horſe and not any Foot, and at his comming thither Mr. <hi>Fines</hi> ſtood in oppoſition againſt him, where Prince <hi>Robert</hi> cauſed his men to diſcharge ſo faſt, inſomuch that there began a great skirmiſh betweene them, holding for the ſpace of two houres: Prince <hi>Robert</hi> with his Forces began to retreat, and at that time the Prince loſt 12. men, and Maſter <hi>Fines</hi> 5. men. The ſaid Prince <hi>Robert</hi> is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:197689:3"/>making of ſpoile, to the great hurt of the ſaid City, and planting of Ordnance, and he hath already ſpoiled and burnt ſome houſes. This Newes was ſent to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons upon Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt, which ſignified that the Kings Majeſty was in perſon at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and that the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> is marching thither with 22000. men. Sent in a Letter from the Honourable Mr. <hi>Fines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſty hauing often times declared his Royall intention and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards this Citty of <hi>London,</hi> hath occationed a great jelouſie in the hearts of divers and allthoughe he hath often times dclared that tumults were puniſhed and ſuppreeſſed he would take his jorney towards this Citty and althoughe ſome peaple weake of opinion that his Majeſty any intention to take his jorney towards this Citty yet by thes perticulers follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, it will moſt evidently and plainely appeere that his Majeſtyes Royall heart
<pb facs="tcp:197689:3"/>hath allwayes beene conioyning to this Citty and it doth moſt manifeſtly teſtify that his Majeſty hath ever and doeth ſtill owe and beare more afection and loue to his ſubjects in this City then he did to any other City in this Kingdom although his Royall and ſacred Majeſty hath beene mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and inſenceb againſt his loueing ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects that are reſident in this Honorable City of <hi>London</hi> by that party which ſeekes dayly to bring the inhabitants here into vtter ruine and deſtruction for as it is the Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efeſt and Metropolitan City of the Kingdome, ſo they ſeeke and labour day ly to bring it to the leaſt and meaneſt eſtat of any City in this Iland or vnder the heavens, and to diſcover and bring to light ſome more of their miſcheeuos and devilliſh intentions which I beleue it is not vnknowne vnto divers that doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand proceedings of cavaleers, and other of the maliguant party of this Kingdome their greateſt malice and envy that is ſo drownded in their hearts that it is almoſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:197689:4"/>impoſſible thing to have us removed, un-God puts his helping hand thereto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Foundation of Reformation is now beginning to take place in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane City, and our Honourable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly the Worthies of <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth now labour and endeavour to bring the ſame to perfection, God of his great mercy ſend his helping hand thereto: But becauſe I will now proceed to the Reſolution and intention of his Sacred Majeſty the King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> concerning this Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and renowned City of <hi>London, (viz)</hi> His Majeſty, as hath been often ſaid, hath had a longing deſire to come neere to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and uſeth the meanes, as it doth accordingly appeare, for upon the 16. day of this month there was a great diſturbance amongſt the Cavaleers at <hi>Darby,</hi> by reaſon that His Majeſty went from thence privately to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> they ſuppoſing he had tooke his journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London,</hi> and indeed it is thought,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:197689:4"/>that although His Perſon be amongſt them yet his heart is better affected towards us, for did not the Cavaleers purſue and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Him ſo cloſe at His removall from one place to another, it is thought that he would ſoone be here, but ſuch is the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of theſe Malignant perſons, that they will not ſuffer His Perſon to be out of their ſight not a minute in a manner, but preſently poſt after him to any place where he goeth; and although His <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty hath often declared to the Cavaleers, that he will venture his life in their defence, yet they are very jealous of his words, and doth daily feare, that hee will come to compoſition with His Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, by reaſon that be doth ſhew ſome countenance to the Parliaments Petitions, and were it not for them, doubtleſſe but we ſhould have him here very ſuddenly. The Honourable Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his Reſolution to his Majeſty, that he is reſolved to put nothing in act, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:197689:5"/>what ſhould tend to his Majeſties honour ſafety and ſecurty, and the good both of Church and Religion, and that to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of His power He will have a wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye, that no outrages and abuſes bee committed by any of his Souldiers, and that His comming now with his Forces is not againſt His Majeſty but againſt the Malignant partie, the wicked incendiaries of this Kingdome that are now about His Royall perſon, whoſe mindes doth daily thirſt after the bloud of our Engliſh and Scots Proteſtants, this is the Noble Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of his Excellence the Earle of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
